Finding Aid for Jean King papers, 1964-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jean King papers 1964-2004
King, Jean.
24 linear feet
88457 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, attorney, feminist, and activist on behalf of equal rights and anti-discrimination organizations and causes; topical files relating to her varied interests and causes; also speech and conference materials; and files documenting her teaching and organizational activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Jean King (donor no. 5119 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions primarily in 2005.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jean Ledwith King has a record of achievement as an attorney, teacher, political activist, and advocate for women. She was born in Chicago, Illinois on March 16, 1924. She received her A.B. in English from the University of Michigan (1948), her M.A. in History from the University of Michigan (1953), and her J.D. from the University of Michigan Law School (1968) where she was also assistant editor of the Michigan Law Review. She was admitted to the bar in 1970.
In addition to her career as an attorney, Jean King has long been politically active as a life-long Democrat involved in local, state, and national party politics. She began in 1959 serving as precinct captain and ward chair in Ann Arbor's Fifth Ward. She has also served as secretary of the Second Congressional District Committee beginning in 1962. In 1967, she was elected to the Democratic State Central Committee as representative from the Second Congressional District. In 1970, she and five other women founded the Women's Caucus of the Michigan Democratic Party. This caucus was the first women's caucus in a major political party. In 1976, the caucus achieved an equal division of males and females on the Michigan national delegation, a model for the rules adopted in 1980 by the national party. Through these and other activities, Jean King became an expert on organization and get-out-the-vote. She thoroughly understands party structure and functioning, and has repeatedly demonstrated ability to anticipate and articulate issues.
The cause of women's rights has been a focus of Jean King's career. In 1970, She was an organizer of FOCUS on Equal Education for Women which filed an administrative complaint with the US Department of Health, Education, and Welfare against the University of Michigan for sex discrimination in admissions, financial aid, academic and non-academic employment, curriculum, athletics, extra curricula activities and services to students. The result was the withholding of $15 million dollars in Federal contracts until the university agreed to eliminate the discriminatory practices. The cause of discrimination and unequal treatment of women engaged in various sports and athletic endeavors became a noteworthy part of her practice.
In 1977, she chaired the Michigan delegation to the International Women's Year Conference in Houston in November of 1977. The Michigan delegation distinguished itself as being the most representative of the women of a state. This delegation was also acclaimed to be one of the best organized and effective groups at the conference.
Jean King has many interests and causes to which she is devoted. She has been a teacher, lecturing widely on the general topic of women and the law, as well as teaching courses at the University of Michigan Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations in 1974, at Washtenaw Community College (beginning in 1974), and Eastern Michigan University (beginning in 1985). She was a member of numerous professional organizations, serving as officer on many of them. These include the Washtenaw County Bar Association, the State Bar of Michigan, the Michigan Trial Lawyers Association, the Washtenaw Trial Lawyers Association, the Women Lawyers of Michigan. She was an active member of the American Civil Liberties Union of Michigan where she served as state vice president (1982-1989); the Washtenaw County branch of the ACLU where she was chair (1982-1989) and long-time member of its Executive Board. A pro-choice activist, Jean King was co-chair of the Michigan Abortion Referendum Campaign in 1972 and founder of the Religious Coalition for Abortion Reform in 1973.
In 1974, she drafted an administrative complaint relating to the sex discrimination in the Houghton-Mifflin text books used in the schools of Kalamazoo, Michigan. As a result o this complaint, the publisher almost immediately issued a supplement and began to revise its books. From this case, King authored a pamphlet entitled "Sex Discrimination in a Elementary Reading Program." In another instance, she argued that common law gave women the right, free of court intervention, to determine their own legal names, and she challenged Michigan's Secretary of State to allow women to use their maiden names on their drivers' licenses. After she personally directed a state-wide campaign joined by thousands of Michigan women, the Secretary of State capitulated.
As an attorney, Jean King has championed the cause of anti-discrimination, equal rights for women, and racial justice. Her courtroom victories have been noteworthy. In one example, a major class action suit (1974-1981) invoking Title VII of the 1965 Civil Rights Act, Jean King helped secure a settlement of $450,000 for 75 female employees of the Kelvinator Company who were judged to be the victims of discrimination (sex, race, and handicap). In addition, her argument that damages under the Michigan Civil Rights Act were not precluded by the workers' compensation law was accepted in a precedent that remains one of the most important weapons in the fight to eliminate sex discrimination in the workplace.
The Jean Ledwith King collection has been arranged into three series: Topical Files; Conferences and speaking engagements; and Organizational Activities. Files from court cases in which Jean King participated as attorney are not part of this finding aid. Such files, kept separate because of the presence of attorney-client privileged communications, are presently unavailable for research.
Subjects:
American Civil Liberties Union.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Sex discrimination against women--Michigan.; United States. Federal Glass Ceiling Commission.; University of Michigan--Administration.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Lawyers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women lawyers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women social reformers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Social reformers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Topical file
  The Topical Files series contains files related to both Jean King's personal, political, and professional life, including files relating to her involvement in community and professional organizations. The series is divided into two subseries, one encompassing topical files dating from the 1960s through the 1980s, and the other focusing on 1987-2004, with some earlier documents and files scattered throughout. Also included are correspondence files filed under the last name of the correspondent. This series contains a significant amount of material related to Jean King's work as a Title IX attorney including files on cases relating to local schools such as the University of Michigan and Huron High School.
  - 1960s-1980s
    - Abortion (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor City Democratic Party (Box 1)
    - Bail denial ballot proposal (Box 1)
    - Brown, Mary (Michigan State Legislator) (Box 1)
    - Democratic Party. Constitutional Convention Commission (Box 1)
    - Democratic Party. Second Congressional District (Box 1)
    - Democratic Party (Michigan), Michigan Women's Political Caucus, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Dessauer, John P. (re. Textbook censorship) (Box 1)
    - Divorce (Jean King article) (Box 1)
    - Eastern Michigan University (Box 2)
    - Ferency, Zolton (Box 2)
    - Fishing License (sex discrimination) (Box 2)
    - Flint Feminists (Box 2)
    - Hammond, Nancy (Box 2)
    - International Women's Year, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Jewell, Ellie (racial harassment in Jackson County school) (Box 2)
    - Kalamazoo Textbook Complaint, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Kalamazoo Study 1969 (Box 2)
    - Little League (Box 2)
    - Marital Rape (removal of exception in the law) (Box 2)
    - National Organization for Women (Michigan) (Box 2)
    - Partnership 1972 (Box 2)
    - Pierce, Edward (Box 2)
    - Professional Women's Caucus 1970 (Box 2)
    - Rape legislation (Box 2)
    - Save the River (Box 2)
    - Sexual discrimination (Box 3)
      - General (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan (HEW complaint against), 18 folders (Box 3)
      - Athletics (Box 4)
    - Sexism: Task Force to Study Sexism in Michigan's Schools 1975 (Box 5)
    - Venereal Disease (Box 5)
    - Vivian (Wes) campaigns (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw Advisory Committee on the Status of Women (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw County Center for the Prevention of Child Abuse (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw County Democratic Conventions (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw County Democrat (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw County Democratic Party (re U-M "union-busting") (Box 5)
    - Wheeler, Albert (regarding recount of election vote) (Box 5)
    - Women's Action Equity League (WEAL) (Box 5)
    - Women's Law Fund 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Women's names (statutes relating to use of maiden names after marriage, etc.) (Box 5)
  - 1987-2004 (with some earlier documents, scattered)
    - Abortion, 12 folders (Box 6)
    - Activist MEA Women's Caucus (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Charter Revision Committee 1989 (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Democratic Party (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Historic District, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Historical Foundation (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor News (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Public Schools (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor School District (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Traffic Signal petition 1969 (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Women's Caucus (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Women's City Club (Box 6)
    - Arbitration (Box 6)
    - Barsamian, Gladys (Box 6)
    - Becket, John (Box 6)
    - Bell Road Bridge (Box 6)
    - Ben Dor, Jan (Box 6)
    - Biographical Files
      - Clippings (Box 6)
      - Compiled Information and Clippings (Box 6)
      - Correspondence 1964-2004, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 7)
        include oral history
      - Photographs (Box 7)
      - Vitas and Speeches (Box 7)
      - Writings and Speeches (Box 7)
    - Brater, Liz (Box 7)
    - Bullard, Perry (Box 7)
    - Cappaert (Box 7)
    - Child Care (Box 7)
    - Child Support Guidelines (Box 7)
    - Coaching Preference to Teachers (Box 7)
    - Coalition to End Legalized Rape (CELR) (Box 7)
    - Coalition for Non-Sexist Education (Box 7)
    - Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW) (Box 7)
    - Committee of Racial/Ethnic and Gender Issues in the Courts (Box 7)
    - Co-ops (Box 7)
    - Co-Housing (Box 7)
    - Crime Victims (Box 7)
    - Davidow, Anne (correspondence) (Box 7)
    - Death Penalty (Box 7)
    - Discrimination (Box 7)
    - Divorce; Marriage (Box 7)
    - Domestic Violence (Box 7)
    - Douglas, Jim (Box 7)
    - Downs, Tom (Box 7)
    - Dry Cleaning, Discrimination In (Box 7)
    - Earrings (Box 7)
    - East, Catherine (Box 7)
    - Eastern Michigan University (Box 7)
    - Fair Housing (Box 7)
    - Faulkner, Shannon (Box 7)
    - Flag, American (Box 7)
    - Ford, Congressman William (Box 7)
    - EMU Faculty (Box 7)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Fair Housing (Box 8)
    - Faulkner, Shannon (Box 8)
    - Flag, American (Box 8)
    - Flint Feminists (Box 8)
    - Ford, Congressman William (Box 8)
    - Francis, Nancy (Box 8)
    - Gender Equality (Box 8)
    - Ginsburg, Ruth Bader (Box 8)
    - Griffiths, Martha (Box 8)
    - Handicapped Juror's issue (Box 8)
    - Harassment in Education Legal Project (HELP) 1984 (Box 8)
    - Hefner, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Hill Auditorium - restroom equity 2002-2004, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Hillary Clinton Fan Club (Box 8)
    - Housing (Box 8)
    - Human Rights Commission (Box 8)
    - Illiteracy (Box 8)
    - Inter-Cooperative Council (Box 8)
    - International Workers of the World (IWW) (Box 8)
    - Levin, Carl (Box 8)
    - Mable (Box 8)
    - MARAL (Box 8)
    - MacDougall, Priscilla (Box 8)
    - Marital Rape (Box 8)
    - Markert, Clement (Box 8)
    - Memorial Advisory & Planning Society (MAPS) (Box 8)
    - Menefee, David (Box 8)
    - Michigan Coalition Against Domestic Violence (Box 8)
    - Michigan Democratic Caucus (Box 8)
    - Michigan Democratic Party (Box 8)
    - Michigan Democratic Party Women's Caucus (Box 8)
    - Michigan Department of Civil Rights (Box 8)
    - Michigan State Bar Foundation, Fellows (Box 8)
    - Michigan Trial Lawyers Association (Box 8)
    - Michigan Women's Campaign Fund (Box 8)
    - Michigan Women's Commission (Box 8)
    - Michigan Women's Historical Center (Box 8)
    - Michigan Women's Political Caucus (Box 8)
    - Names (Box 8)
    - Name Change (Box 8)
    - National Women & Law Conference (Box 8)
    - National Organization of Women (NOW), 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Packard Clinic (Box 9)
    - Pay Equity (Box 9)
    - Peace Neighborhood Center (Box 9)
    - PEER (Box 9)
    - Pipers, Kitty, videotape (Box 9)
    - Police in Schools (Box 9)
    - Pollack, Lana (Box 9)
    - Power, Sarah (Box 9)
    - Powsner, Rhoda (Box 9)
    - PPO (Box 9)
    - Pregnancy (Box 9)
    - Punchcards (Box 9)
    - Rape (Box 9)
    - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) (Box 9)
    - Rent Control (Box 9)
    - Rivers, Lynn (Box 9)
    - Roberts, Cokie (Box 9)
    - Safehouse (Box 9)
    - Salem Historical Society (Box 9)
    - Sallade, George (Box 9)
    - Sardinha (Box 9)
    - Schembechler (Box 9)
    - Senior Law Day 1991 (Box 9)
    - Sex Discrimination
      - General, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - in Credit (Box 9)
      - Detroit (Box 9)
      - in Education (Box 9)
      - in Employment (Box 9)
      - in High School Athletics (Box 9)
      - in Sports (Box 9)
    - Sexism in Advertising (Box 9)
    - Sexual Assault (Box 9)
    - Sexual Harassment, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Shafer, Ann (Box 9)
    - Shecter, Lynn H. (Box 9)
    - Sickon, Bridget (Box 9)
    - Small Claims Court (Box 9)
    - Smith, Alma (Box 9)
    - Sodomy (Box 9)
    - Soundings, A Center for Women (Box 9)
    - Spayth, Verna (Box 9)
    - Speaking Dates (Box 9)
    - Sports, Title IX (Box 10)
      - General
        - General File (Box 10)
        - FOIA Requests (Box 10)
        - Guide to Title IX and Intercollegiate Sports (Box 10)
        - Harris: Reform of Women's Intercollegiate Athletics (Box 10)
        - Press Releases (Box 10)
        - Speech (Box 10)
      - Heckman, Diane (Box 10)
      - Montgomery, Jolyn, North Dakota State University 1993 (Box 10)
      - By Sport:
        - Baseball, Pro 1992 (Box 10)
        - Field Hockey (Box 10)
        - Ice Hockey (Box 10)
        - Lacrosse (Box 10)
        - Soccer (Box 10)
        - Volleyball (Box 10)
        - Wrestling (Box 10)
      - By College:
        - Brown University 1992 (Box 10)
        - California State University (Box 10)
        - Colgate University (Box 10)
        - Ferris State University (Box 10)
        - Hobart and Smith Colleges (Box 10)
        - Kent State University (Box 10)
        - MSU Basketball (Box 10)
        - University of Michigan
          - Title IX Complaint 1973 (Box 10)
          - Sex Discrimination, Stag dinners 1991-1992 (Box 10)
          - Sports General (Box 10)
        - University of Toledo, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - By High School:
        - Aurora West (Box 10)
        - Dearborn High School 1995 (Box 10)
        - Huron High School (Box 10)
        - Ohio High School (Box 10)
        - Ohio Wesleyan High School (Box 10)
        - North Shores Jr. High School (Box 10)
        - Pioneer High School (Box 10)
    - Sports, Women and (Box 11)
    - State Bar of Michigan (Box 11)
    - Steiner, Julie (Box 11)
    - Stephens, Judge Cynthia (Box 11)
    - Stewardesses (Box 11)
    - Strong, Jerome, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Tannis, Leslie (Box 11)
    - Task Force on Athletics (Box 11)
    - Three Sisters Lake 1970-1973, 1997 (Box 11)
    - Time Magazine (Box 11)
    - Timm, Larry (Box 11)
    - Topless (Box 11)
    - Tort Reform (Box 11)
    - Toussaint (Box 11)
    - Toxic Tort (Box 11)
    - Treasurer, County (Box 11)
    - Tucker automobile (Box 11)
    - UAW (Box 11)
    - University of Michigan, 21 folders (Box 11)
      include material on FOCUS organization
    - Veteran Feminist Association Herstory Project interview with Jean King 2003, VHS videotape (Box 11)
    - Walker, Fleet (Box 11)
    - Walz, Mona (Box 11)
    - Washtenaw County Bar Association, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Washtenaw County Judiciary Commission (Box 11)
    - Washtenaw Trial Lawyers Association (Box 11)
    - Women's Coalition for the 3rd Century (Box 11)
    - Women's Conference of Concerns (Box 11)
    - Women's Equity Action League, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Box 12)
    - Women Judges (Box 12)
    - Women and the Law Conference (Box 12)
    - Women's Law Fund (Box 12)
    - Women Lawyers Association of Michigan, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Women Legislators (Box 12)
    - Women's Equity Action League (Box 12)
    - Zeta Tau Alpha (Box 12)
    - Zull, Peggy & Roger Couch (Box 12)
    - Zwerdling (Box 12)
- Conferences and speaking engagements 1973-1994
  The Conferences and speaking engagements series dates from 1973 to 1994 with several gaps. Included in the files are speeches, conferences attended, and other invitational materials.
  - 1973 October 1975-October 1976 (Box 13)
  - November 1976-January 1978 (Box 14)
  - February 1978-December 1979 (Box 15)
  - January-December 1980 (lacking 1981) (Box 16)
  - January-August 1982 (Box 17)
  - December 1982-December 1985 (1984 is sparse) (Box 18)
  - January-December 1986 (Box 19)
  - 1994 (Box 19)
  - Scattered speeches on topics (Box 19)
- Organizational Activities
  The Organizational Activities series relates to some Jean King's activities with the Federal Glass Ceiling and the American Civil Liberties Union, and to the classes taught at Eastern Michigan University and Washtenaw Community College. Her involvement in other organizations is scattered throughout the Topical Files.
  - Federal Glass Ceiling Commission
    - Working files (Box 20)
    - Working files (Box 21)
      (continued)
    - Working files (Box 22)
  - American Civil Liberties Union
    - Working files (Box 23)
  - Eastern Michigan University
    - Course Materials for class taught by JK (Box 24)
  - Washtenaw Community College
    - Course Materials for class taught by JK (Box 24)